In planning this lesson, we knew we wanted to focus on highway driving,
在准备这个课程时 虽然我们知道我们的重点是讲述高速路上的驾驶
but we still debated what states we should use for our finite state machine.
但是 我们仍然不太确定我们的有限状态机将使用哪些状态
We quickly agreed on three,
很快 我们确定了三种状态
since it seemed to us like these were
因为 在我们看来
the bare minimum and that a single lane change wouldn't suffice.
这三种状态是最基本的最小集合 而仅仅一个车道变换状态显然是不够的
And we also agreed to rule out a lot of states because most of
我们同时也排除掉了许多其他状态
these can be thought of as various implementations of the keep lane state.
因为大部分这些状态可以看做是维持车道状态的不同实现
But these last two, prepare lane change
对于其他两种我们选择的状态 准备向左车道变换
left and prepare lane change right, we were unsure about.
和准备向左车道变换 我们也并不是特别确定是否要选择
Eventually, we did decide to use these states for these lessons.
但是 最后 我们还是决定在本课程中使用这两种状态
So we should probably clarify what we mean by these states.
所以我们或许应该阐明一下我们使用这些状态的目的何在
Let's start by imagining what vehicle behavior would
让我们设想一下 如果没有这两种预先状态
look like without these two prep states.
机动车的行为将会如何
First, let me explain how this example will work.
首先 让我解释一下这个例子如何工作
Up here we have a two-lane highway with traffic driving to the right.
这里有一个两车道高速路 上面有向右的车辆在行驶
This is our self-driving car and other traffic is shown in red.
这是我们的无人车 别的车辆用红色标识
As you watch this animation,
当你看这个动画的时候
you should imagine watching from a helicopter which is flying
你可以设想你正在一架直升机上向下看
above the highway at the self-driving car's target speed.
直升机和无人车目标速度相同
These red trails indicate the relative speed of other vehicles.
这些红色线条指示出别的车辆的相对速度
In this situation, the vehicles in lane one are moving faster
在这种情况下 车道一上的车辆移动得比无人车快
than we are while the vehicles in lane two are moving slower.
车道二上的车辆移动得比无人车慢
When we only have three states plus a fourth ready state,
当我们只有三种状态 以及第四种“就绪”状态时
the finite state machine looks like this.
有限状态机看起来像这样
We'll assume that as we begin watching we are already in the keep lane state.
我们假设 当我们开始观察时 我们已经处于保持车道状态
Now before we watch what happens to our vehicle when it uses this finite state machine,
现在 在我们观测我们使用有限状态机的车辆接下来会怎么做之前
let me explain what these states mean.
让我来解释一下这些状态的含义
The lane keep state attempts to stay in
保持车道状态试图通过保持车辆位置在接近车道中线附近
the current lane by staying near the center line for that lane.
来保持在当前车道行驶
So thinking in finite coordinates,
所以 考虑下限定坐标
we might just say that target d for the vehicle is whatever the d for the lane is.
我们可以说目标 d 对于该车而言等同于 d 对于车道的情况
And for the s direction,
但是对于 s 方向
keep lane state attempts to drive at the vehicle's target speed when that's feasible,
保持车道状态则试图以可行的目标车速行驶
but when it's not, it will try to drive at whatever speed is safest for the lane.
如果目标车速不可行 那么该车会以某个该车道上的最安全车速行驶
For lane changes the goal is to move from the initial lane to the target lane.
对于车道变换 目标是从最初的车道移动到目标车道
The d behavior is what you might expect to move left or right as appropriate.
d 行为表示你可能期待根据情况从左向右移动
So the target d is the d for whatever lane is to
所以目标 d 意味着
the left or right of the ego's current lane.
ego 车当前车道两侧车道上的任意点
For s, the same rules as lane keeping apply.
保持车道的规则同样适用于 s
The vehicle will try to drive at the target speed,
车辆将试图以目标速度行驶
but if that's not feasible,
但是 如果那个速度行不通
then it will drive at whatever speed is safe for the initial lane.
那么 他将以某种安全速度行驶
Now, let's observe the vehicle's behavior as we move forward in time.
现在 让我们观察车辆的行为 当我们及时向前移动
For the first few timesteps,
对于最开始的几个时间步进
we see that the ego-vehicle gets closer and closer to vehicle
我们看到 当左边车道上的车辆超过 ego 的时候
2.2 while the vehicle in the left lane pas the ego-vehicle.
ego 车越来越接近 2.2 车
And during this time the vehicle remains in the lane keep state
然后 在这个时间段中 这辆车继续留在保持车道状态中
since there isn't really enough gap to make a safe lane change.
因为没有足够的空档来做安全变道操作
Note that at this point the ego-vehicle does
注意 此时 ego 开始减速了
begin to slow down even though it doesn't change state.
即使状态未更改
That's because the lane keep state contains this behavior.
因为保持车道状态包含减速行为
When the target speed is no longer feasible,
当目标速度不可能
it will adjust speed to something safe for the lane.
它会调到安全速度
At this point, the vehicle has decided that the lane change left is the best move.
此时 该车决策到 左变道是最佳操作
Now, in the lane change state,
现在 处于变道状态
you can see the vehicle has moved left in its lane but hasn't adjusted its speed.
大家可以看到 该车开始左移 但是速度没变
This is consistent with the rules we defined for lane change behavior.
这与我们预先定义的变道行为一致
At this point, the vehicle has crossed the dotted line,
这时候 该车已经越过车道线
so its current lane is the left lane.
变道成功
Now it wants to transition back to the lane keep state to stay in this lane,
现在 它希望切回到车道保持状态
and when it does that,
然后当切换成功
it immediately starts accelerating so it can get to a speed that's safe for this lane.
它马上开始加速 达到新车道的安全车速
Right now it is moving at the same speed as other traffic in the left lane,
现在 它和左边车道上的车辆以同样速度行驶
which it can continue doing until it passes the vehicles on the right.
它会保持该速度 直到它越过右边车道上的车辆
Even though this worked, there were some problems.
尽管以上操作会成功 但是这里还有些问题
First, even when it was clear that there was
首先 即使左边有个明显空档
a gap we could probably move into on the left,
因此我们可以进入左边车道
we had no way to tell the vehicle to try to get alongside that gap.
但是我们没有办法告诉车辆 让它主动和空档并行
We had to just wait for the gap to get close to us.
我们不得不等待 直到空档靠近我们
Second, this lane change wasn't all that safe.
其次 这种变道不是那么安全
Ideally, we would have been able to get closer to
理想情况下 在真正变道前
the left lane speed before actually making the lane change.
我们可以接近左边车道的车速
Third, it isn't clear when we would have turned on the turn signal in this scenario.
第三 在这个场景中 何时我们打开转向灯 我们并不清楚
The turn signal is the responsibility of the behavior team and
打开灯的信号是行为团队的职责
ideally we would like to turn it on
理想情况下 在我们具体进行车道变换前几秒钟
a few seconds before we actually start changing lanes.
我们希望打开它
Using this finite state machine,
使用这个有限状态机
it would have been hard to do that.
做到这一点比较困难
To address that problem,
为了解决上述问题
we can introduce a prepare for lane change state.
我们可以引入一个变道准备状态
In this state we do whatever we can to prepare for a lane change left or right,
在这个状态中 我们做变道前准备 无论是向左还是向右
which means in the d directions we still can
哪意味着在 d 方向 我们仍然能够
stay in this current lane but in the s direction we
待在当前车道 但是在 s 方向
tried to match the position and speed of some gap in one of the adjacent lanes.
我们将试图匹配相邻车道空档的位置和速度
This is also when we would turn on the appropriate signal.
这也是我们打开转向指示灯的时间
We also changed the finite state machine to look like this.
我们也改变状态机 它起来像这样
And note that the only way to change lanes is to first prepare for a lane change.
注意 变道操作之前必定有一个准备变道状态
Let's see what that would look like.
我们来看看具体过程
At the first timestep we can decide to prepare
在第一个步进时间点上 通过追踪这里的空档
for a lane change by tracking this gap over here,
我们能够决定 开始准备一个变道操作
which allows us to immediately start slowing down.
此操作会让我们马上开始减速
At this point, the car may begin slowly increasing
在这个时间点上 车辆也许开始慢慢加速
speed to get closer to the left lane speed,
以接近左边车道的速度
and at this point the vehicle has reached the same speed as the left lane traffic
然后在这个点上 车辆已经达到左边车道车辆行驶速度
and is in a good position to execute a lane change, which it begins here.
并且处于换道操作的有利位置
From here on, everything looks pretty similar to before.
从这时候开始 所有事情看起来和以前非常相似
With these added states,
通过这些添加的状态
we're now able to perform a lane change more safely and efficiently.
现在 我们可以更加安全有效地进行换道操作